她如影随形
It's so close.
几千年以来人们因为她的存在而得到欣慰
For thousands of years, Man has found comfort in its presence.
她是旅行家夜晚的灯塔
It's been a beacon for nocturnal travelers,
是农夫的计时器
a timekeeper for farmers,
水手在海上的航标
and a location finder for sailors at sea.
某些文明甚至把她作为神灵
For some cultures it's even been a god.
她是人类唯一造访过的宇宙天体
It's the only cosmic body ever visited by human beings.
而且现在美国航天局计划在那建立永久基地
And today NASA is planning a permanent outpost there.
她是如何被放到首位的？
But how did it get there in the first place?
月亮是如何到来的呢？
How did the Moon come to be?
答案充满了惊奇和吸引力
The answer is more astounding and spectacular
超过了地球上大多数人的想象
than most residents of Earth have ever imagined.
--==本影片由 CMCT 团队 荣誉出品==--
更多精彩影视 请访问 http://www.hdcmct.com
历史频道·宇宙第一季第5集 月球
影片压制:暮云春树  字幕来源：射手网 调校：TIAN@CMCT 招募Q号: 76846146
根据最新统计 太阳系里有150多颗卫星
At last count, over 150 moons populate our solar system.
海王星有13颗
Neptune claims 13 of them.
土星有48颗
Saturn has 48.
木星竟然有62颗
And Jupiter host an astounding 62.
另一方面地球却只有一颗
Earth, on the other hand, has just one.
然而她却是特别的一颗
But it's a special one.
我们的卫星--露娜(月神) 罗马人取的名字 有着不一般的大小
Our moon, Luna, as the Romans named it, is remarkable in its size.
她不是太阳系里最大的卫星
It is by no means the largest moon in the solar system.
其它几个要比她大
Several others are bigger.
土星的一颗卫星提坦(土卫六)就是个例子 体积是月亮的两倍
One of Saturn's moon's Titan for instance, is twice the size.
不过月亮对于地球却是最大的
But our moon is the largest, in relation to its host planet.
她有地球的四分之一大小 与地球相比实在是大
It's a quarter the size of the Earth, It's really big compared to the Earth.
如果你用望远镜在远距离观望地球
If you look to a telescope, at the Earth from a distance
你将看到地球和这个大东西
you'd see the Earth and this other big thing.
如果你看木星或其它行星
If you look at Jupiter, or any other planet,
只能看到巨大的行星和所有微小的卫星在它的旁边 所以…
you got the big planet and all tiny moons right next to it. So…
我们的月亮要大得多 她只是…
our moon is so much bigger, and it's the only one of the…
现在的八颗行星之一 就是这个情况
of the now eight planets, that has that situation.
两者的相对大小如此接近
The relative sizes of the two bodies are close enough,
某些天文学家很早就提及"地-月系统"
that some astronomers goes so far as to refer to the "Earth-moon system"
就象个双行星
as a double planet.
地球到月亮的平均距离为234000英里
The mean distance from the Earth to the Moon is 234,000 miles.
为期3天的飞行距离
A three-day fly through space.
月球的直径大约为地球的四分之一
Luna's diameter is roughly one quarter the size of Earth,
2160英里
measuring 2,160 miles.
月球上的一天相当于地球的27.3天
A single day on the Moon is the equivalent of 27.3 Earth days.
这是因为月球的一面始终对着我们
This is because one side of the Moon permanently faces us.
月球一面固定对着地球
Luna is face-locked with our planet.
因此月球必须是足足围绕地球转一圈
So the Moon must fully orbit the Earth, in order to make
才能围绕着自己的轴线自转一圈
one complete rotation on its axes.
就象孩子们玩的"围着萝西转圈圈"的游戏
Sort of like children in a game of "Ring around the Rosie".
孩子们的脸始终朝着里面 手拉着手转着圈子
They always face inward, as they hold hands and move in a circle.
0 点火 升空 已经升空…
Zero, all engines running. Liftoff. We have a liftoff…
然而月球对地球是如此的密切
Yet as closely related as the Moon is to our Earth,
对月球不仅仅是短暂的旅行 十分清楚
it would only take a brief visit to Luna, to make it quite clear
事实上她与地球非常地不同
that it is in fact a very different world from our planet.
这是一个非常危险的地方
And an exceedingly dangerous place.
我们站在这 安静极了 鹰已经登陆
We're standing now. Tranquility base here. The Eagle has landed.
当然没有空气 你需要太空服
There's no air of course. You need your space suit.
确实月球完全没有大气层
Indeed, the Moon has absolutely no atmosphere at all.
所以声音无法传播
So there is nothing to carry sound waves.
如果你和朋友站在月球上试图交流
If you were standing on the Moon with a friend, and trying to converse,
他是无法听到你说什么的 除非用无线电
the person wouldn't be able to hear you. Except by radio.
我在月球上漫步了一天
I was strolling on the Moon one day,
在快乐 快乐的…
in the merry, merry month of…
-十二月 -不 是五月
- December. - No, May!
没有大气层也意味着没有空气分子
No atmosphere also means that there are no air molecules
弥散太阳来的光线
to scatter light from the Sun.
所以天空始终是黑暗的
So the sky is always black.
地形对前景边亮少许有点帮助
And the landscape does little to help brighten the scene.
单色调的 你知道吗没有很多颜色
Kind of monochromatic, you know, not much color there,
岩石几乎是灰褐色的
The rocks are mostly gray-brown colors.
她在一个方向上可能有点暖色调的 可能是向着太阳的缘故
It's maybe a little warmer tone in one direction, maybe towards the Sun, and
而在其它方向去看 就是冷色调的 灰色调的
cooler tones, grayer tones, looking in other directions,
不是五颜六色的
but not so colorful.
极端的温度也是大煞游览的风景
Extreme temperatures will also add to the unpleasantness of a visit.
冷热之间温度摆动是严酷的
The swings between hot and cold are brutal.
从正午的270度
From 270 degrees above zero at mid-day,
到晚上的零下240度
to 240 degrees below zero at night.
甚至月球的低引力只有地球的六分之一
Even the Moon's low gravity, just one sixth of Earth's,
对旅游者是个冒险的举动
could present a hazard to a tourist.
现实中阿波罗宇航员在月球上漫步时
A reality the Apollo astronauts kept at the tops of their minds
要保持了高度的思想集中
during their many moonwalks.
他们意识到在他们太空服
They realize that beyond the thickness
的外面是死亡
of their visor in their space suit, was death.
他们做事时会被岩石绊倒
Should they do something and fall into a rock
失足被露出的岩石击中
and lose your footing and fall and hit an outcrop,
面罩会被打碎 把自己暴露在月球的真空里
this visor could be cracked, expose you to lunar vacuum,
这样就会是一个严重的情况
we would had a serious situation on our hand.
即使太空服可以对付月球的真空
But while a spacesuit could protect lunar tourists against the vacuum of space,
月球上缺乏氧气 温度极端 还有致命的太阳辐射
a lack of oxygen, temperature extremes, and lethal solar radiation,
但是太空服提供的有限的保护还是无法避免潜在的危险
a potential hazard that spacesuit would do little to protect against,
就是高速的微小陨石
is high-velocity micro-meteorites.
它们连续打击月球的表面
They pummel the lunar surface frequently.
细小的陨石…
Tiny meteorites…
在我们大气层燃烧和产生流星的小陨石
The little ones that burn up in our atmosphere and make shooting stars,
那些 月球上没有大气 它们就直接打击表面
those, there's no atmosphere on Moon, they're coming right down hitting surface.
它们研磨着月球表面
They pulverize the lunar surface,
产生了轻物质的沙尘飞扬 所谓的风化层
generating a dusty blanket of gravel light material, called regolith.
阿曼达·汉德里克斯博士在美国航天局的喷气推进实验室里研究月球
Doctor Amanda Hendrix studies the moon at NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory.
这是普通工厂里的工具
This clamp here is kind of a regular factory.
它研磨石块 就是那
It's ground up rock, that's what it is.
随着时间推移 研磨会快得多
The times goes and this scrubber mill a lot faster.
这至少磨了一个小时了
Here it's made in less than an hour,
然而在月球上 已经经历了40亿年的轰击
but on the Moon, it is the result of more than four billion years of bombardment,
陨石和小陨石降落在表面 破碎了岩石
by meteorites and micro meteorites, raining in on the surface and breaking up the rock.
就象这个研磨机的产物
Like the product of this gravel mill,
月球风化层以各种各样的颗粒组成
lunar regolith has formed in a variety of grain sizes,
从大石块到细沙
from large rocks to fine dust.
这个非常细的沙尘对我们是熟悉的 在来自阿波罗的图象里
This very fine dust is familiar to us from Apollo images that
宇航员黄昏的足迹里可以看到
were seen of astronaut's footprints in the dusk.
那非常细而且…事实上细到给宇航员造成麻烦
It's very fine and… So fine, in fact, that the astronauts had problems with it.
粘住他们的太空服 进入他们的设备里
Sticking to their spacesuits, getting into the equipment
并且最终导致出现一些问题
and it can end up causing a bit of a problem.
过去也确实有大的陨石打击月球
Really big meteorites have also hit the Moon in the past.
事实上那些大的打击
In fact, these massive impacts
造成了月球上暗的圆形区域
are responsible for the dark circular regions on the lunar surface.
许多观察者看到的形状
The shapes that to many observers
象人的眼睛 鼻子和嘴巴那样排列
seem to be arranged like the eyes, nose and mouth of a human face.
这使人们对月球产生了幻象
They make up the illusion of the man on the moon.
那是月球表面巨大撞击的痕迹
They blasted huge basins in the Moon surface.
有些有700英里宽
Some of them are 700 miles across.
在撞击的地方黑色的火山岩喷出 充满了盆地
Dark lava eventually burst through at the impact points, and flooded the basins.
今 我们把这些暗的区域称为玛丽亚 拉丁文中对海洋的词汇
Today, we call these dark regions, maria, the Latin word for seas.
可以追溯到17世纪
They states back to the 17th century,
文艺复兴时期的观星者观察月球
when Renaissance Era observers looked up at the Moon.
他们推测那些暗区可能是海洋
They speculated that the dark areas might be oceans.
那时的天文学家给许多暗的区域或者海洋起了古里古怪的名字
And astronomers of the time gave the many dark spots, or seas, whimsical names.
所有海洋被命名的结果曾经作为月球的象征
The seas are all named after effects that were once attributed to the Moon.
所以就有了风暴海 危机海 还有宁静海
So you have the Sea of Storms and the Sea of Crisis, and the Sea of Tranquility,
以及往前…
and so forth…
有些年轻的撞击盆地侵蚀时间较短
Some of the younger impact basins have had less time to erode,
所以它们的特性还是比较脆弱
so their features are still relatively crisp.
一个细节是叫做东方暗区或者叫东方之海
One in particular is called Mare Orientale, or the Eastern Sea.
它有600英里宽 是一次撞击产生的结果
It's some 600 miles across, and the impact that created it,
撞击是如此的沉重和直接
was so massive and direct.
看上去非常象靶子上公牛的眼睛
The result looks very much like the bull's eye on a target.
这个东方之海就象子弹射在玻璃上
This Orientale scar is kind of like a bullet shot in the glass, where you see all the
能够看到全部的环状物 碎片喷出来
the sort of rings around it and fractures going out.
人们经常说 如果她处在直接对着地球的一面
People have often said that if it had been on the side facing directly toward you,
我们就可能会有月球的其它神话了
we might have had a whole different mythology about the Moon,
这是因为她就象一个大眼睛注视着我们
because it will look like a big eye staring at us.
三个山脉组成的同心环围绕着东方之海
Three concentric rings of mountain ranges surround Mare Orientale,
有些山峰高达几千英尺
and some of the peaks rise to several thousand feet.
它们是猛烈冲击的产物
They're all effects of the monster impact.
当我们在地球上看到环型山 这些首先是由
When we see mountain ranges on the Earth, they're mostly caused first by
周围的陆地运动造成的 陆地相互之间的运动非常缓慢
the continents moving around, crashing into each other very slowly, buckling up and
折皱产生环型山 并且在水的侵蚀以后
creating mountain ranges which then erode into all that spectacular
才形成我们在马特洪峰看到的壮观景象
shapes that we see at the Matterhorn and so forth, from water erosion.
在月球上没有大陆板块运动
On the Moon, there are no continental plate tectonics.
表面是静止的
The surface is static.
是的 在月球上还是能看到山脉
Yeah. You still have mountains on the Moon
原因在于那些巨大的撞击盆地
and the reason is that those big impact basins.
那是一个巨大的喷发陷坑
That's big explosion excavates a pit,
物体投掷在外面 所以会有环形山
throws the material up on the outsides, so you have these rings of mountains,
弧形山包围着撞击的地点
arcs of mountains, that surround the impact sites.
然而这些撞击特征是由外部力量引发的
But their impact features in there is caused by the external forces,
而不是内部力量引起的
not the internal forces.
另一个引人注目的撞击坑 要比东方之海小许多
Another notable impact crater, much smaller than Mare Orientale,
但非常壮观 叫第谷
but every bit as spectacular, is Tycho.
是以17世纪一位著名的丹麦天文学家的名字命名的
Named after a prominent 17th century Danish astronomer,
这个撞击坑
this impact feature
坐落在月球西南方的边缘处
is located in the southwestern quadrant on the Moon's near side.
它是…在明亮的区域 用肉眼几乎就能看到它
It's… in the bright area, you could have almost see it with the naked eye.
当它爆发时 就象其它许多弹坑一样
And when that explosion happened as with many other craters
喷射出明亮的粉尘
it shot out jets of bright powdery dust,
所以这些喷发的放射状条纹很清楚
so that these rays that got out from it were very stripy.
喷射出来的放射状物质从第谷的碰撞点向外延展了900英里
The rays of dusty ejected material extends some 900 miles from the Tycho impact site.
一座残留的山体也在弹坑的中心升起
A mountain of debris also rises from the center of the crater.
这是小行星撞击的反作用力造成的
This is a result of recoil from the asteroid's strike.
在那个撞击点中心的一些被高速压扁的物质
Some of the highly compressed material at the center of the impact site
向外弹出 一旦撞击 要么弹起 要么粉碎
springs outward, once the impacting body either ricochets or disintegrates.
然而长期以来所有的月球特征
But long before any of the Moon specific features
都已经通过望远镜和太空旅行了解清楚了
could be discern through sophisticated telescopes and space travel,
对月球的外貌和举止行为的仔细观察
careful observation of the lunar behavior and appearance
对地球的居民来说仍然是至关重要的
was still vitally important to Earth dwellers.
至少在15000年里 人类敬仰月亮作为光的来源
For 15,000 years at least, Man revered the Moon as a source of light,
作为航海的指南
as a navigational guide,
作为农业生产的参考
as a reference in agricultural pursuits.
而最重要的是…作为方便的计时器
And most of all… as a convenient timekeeper.
在现代社会之前的日子里 计时可不是件容易的事
In the days before our modern systems, timekeeping was no simple task.
早期的计时有两种选择
Early timekeepers had two choices:
依靠太阳或者月亮
they could monitor the Sun or the Moon.
如果你想记录日期
If you think about trying to keep track of dates,
如果你用我们现在使用的阳历计时
if you use a solar calendar like we do nowadays,
一年就有365天 那就要持续记录大量的天数
there are 365 days in a year, and that's an awful lot of days to keep track of,
这是一件平常人难以做好的事情
and it's not something that the ordinary person could do very well.
相对的是用阴历 谁都会告诉你月亮什么时候处在满月
Compare that with a lunar calendar. Everybody can tell when the full moon is
月亮什么时候处在新月 用不着看月亮是不是新月
when the new moon is, you don't see the moon at new moon,
只要将月亮与满月做个比较很容易就告诉你了
you see it as big and round at full moon so it's easy to tell,
月亮的周期只有28或29天 很容易计算
there are only 28 or 29 days in a lunar cycle, so it's easy to count them
所以大多数民族还是用阴历的
and so most societies actually started out with a lunar calendar.
早期的月球观察家也承认那颗我们星球的伙伴
Early observers of the Moon also recognize that our planetary neighbor
对地球有着非常的物理作用
has a very real physical effect on the Earth itself.
月球与我们的海洋的潮汐涨落有关
The Moon is responsible for the rise and fall of our ocean tides.
如果月球是这个网球
If I think of the Moon as being this tennis ball
地球是这个足球
and the Earth as being this football,
潮汐是由月球的引力引起的
the tides are caused by the Moon's gravitational attraction,
这是显而易见的…这样 月球的力量牵引着地球上的水
so it's obvious… Ok, so the Moon kind of pulls the Earth's water towards it.
所以这造成了朝着月球的方向稍微有些隆起
And so this creates a slight bulge in the direction of the Moon.
同样在背对月球方向的地方也稍微有些隆起
Well, it's less obvious that there's also a bulge in the direction away from the Moon,
这事实上就是每天两次高潮的原因
so there is in fact two high tides every day.
其它高潮你能够想象到是由
The other high tide you can think of is being caused
地球的向心力引起的
by the Earth's centripetal force.
地球和月球两者轮流运转 引起
The Earth and the Moon are both rotating around, and that causes
远处的水同样运动
the water on the far side to also move out.
涨潮和落潮之间差异的一个极端的例子
An extreme illustration of the difference between high and low tides
可以在加拿大芬迪湾看到
can be found along the shore of Canada's Bay of Fundy.
涨潮和落潮之间的落差
The water level from high tide to low tide
竟然达到55英尺
drops an astounding 55 feet.
对地球上的某些生命来说
For some forms of life on Earth,
涨潮和落潮创造了有益的环境
the advance and retreat of the tides creates useful habitats.
然而月球对我们星球的另一个引力作用
But another of the Moon's gravitational effect on our planet
是直接作用陆地生存的生命
is directly responsible for nothing less than the continued survival of terrestrial life itself.
月球稳定地球的气候 月球的引力
The Moon stabilizes Earth's climate. The gravitational effect of the Moon
使得地球的自转轴倾斜保持在一定的角度
keeps the degree of tilt on the Earth's rotational axis constant.
这个倾斜保持了季节的周期
This tilt is what maintains the repeatable cycle of seasons,
随着地球围绕太阳运转
as the Earth orbits the Sun.
如果我们没有月球 如果我们没有一个小许多的月球 举个例子
If we didn't have the Moon, or if we had a much smaller Moon, for example,
可以通过计算看出
then you can mathematically show,
我们的北极的倾斜会有很大差别
that the tilt of our north pole would vary widely,
换角度来说从0到90度 现在是23.5度
with that angle going, from, say, 0 to 90 degrees, currently it's 23.5 degrees,
事实上那将会很混乱
and it would actually vary chaotically.
所以月球在稳定我们的旋转轴
And so the Moon has played an important role in the stability
稳定我们星球和气候方面扮演了重要的角色
of our axis of rotation, of our planet and therefore in our climate.
在过去的年代里 由于月球
Over the millennia, with the Moon's prominent
始终如一地挂在天空
and constant presence in our night sky,
人们终于开始推测她的来历
man ultimately began to speculate on its origin.
她是如何形成的？月球是怎么来的？
How did it form? How did the Moon come to be?
公元前455年 希腊学者 安那克萨哥拉
In 455 BCE the Greek scholar Anaxagoras
推断月球只是地球甩出去的一块石头
theorized that the Moon was simply a rock that was flung off by the Earth.
而此时大多数他的同时代的人
Most of his contemporaries, on the other hand,
却深信月球是神灵
were convinced that the Moon was a god,
或可能是个巨大的火球
or maybe a huge ball of fire.
所以 安那克萨哥拉 的想法没有得到更多的关注
So Anaxagoras' notion did not get much attraction.
冷静的思考毫无疑问还在继续
Quiet speculation no doubt continued,
但一直到1609年都还没有过硬的说法
but no hard information about the Moon came until 1609.
当意大利天文学家伽利略
When Italian astronomer Galileo Galilei
首次用望远镜对准月球时
pointed one of the first telescopes at the Moon,
验证了他所看到的景观是另一个世界的地形
recognized that he was looking at a landscape, the terrain of another world.
当你通过望远镜观看月球
When you look at the Moon through a telescope,
看到情况与肉眼看到完全不同
it looks completely different from the way it looks to the naked eye.
所以肉眼看到的平坦的景象被替代了
So instead of looking flat the way it does to the naked eye,
环望四周 都是阴影
it really looks round, and you can see the shadows,
看到的都是弹坑 肉眼是看不到的
you can see all these craters that a naked eye just not see,
只是一眼看上去象个宇宙
and it just immediately looks like a world,
从三维世界里跳了出来
it jumps out at you into three dimensions.
伽利略详细地描绘了小行星的表面
Galileo made detailed drawings of the small planet's surface,
并且永远确立了月球是固体的星球
and established once and for all that the Moon is a solid world,
不是神灵或火球
not a god or a fireball.
然而这位天文开拓者从未公开推测月球的起源
But the groundbreaking astronomer never publicly speculated on the Moon's origin.
首先是因为他假设那是颗其它的行星
Primarily because he hasn't assume move to other planets.
不过直到1873年
Not until 1873
关于月球起源的科学理论才
did the first science based theory regarding the origin of the Moon
首次公开发表
publicly emerge.
是从天才的法国天文学家爱德华·洛希头脑里涌现出来
It sprang from the mind of a talented French astronomer named Edouard Roche.
洛希鼓吹所谓的共同成长理论
Roche advocated for what's called the co-accretion theory,
那主要是表明
which says that basically
地球和月球是在同一时间形成 由相同物质组成的
Earth and the Moon grew up at the same time, out of the same materials.
那时许多科学家开始相信
In Roche's days many scientists began to believe
行星是由冷凝的气体云形成的
that the planets might have formed from hot condensing clouds of gas.
它逐渐收缩冷却 并且随着收缩
It gradually contracted and cooled and as it contracted,
分离气体环
it would separate out rings of gas, so you'd have
所以气体环在这里 一个环在这里 等等
a ring of gas here, a ring here and so forth.
这些气体环最后终于凝结形成行星
And these rings of gas would then eventually coalesce and form the planets.
洛希说地球和月球是太阳系的缩影
Roche saw the Earth and the Moon as a solar system in miniature.
他的想法是地球开始时是个气体球
His idea was that the Earth starts out as a ball of gas
在冷却收缩时散发出气体环
and then cools and contracts and sheds a ring of gas,
然后环自身粘合形成月球
that then itself coalesces and forms the Moon.
然而这个理论有问题
But there are problems with this theory.
一个问题是月球的铁含量要比地球的铁含量小得多
For one our Moon has a much lower iron content than the Earth.
如果两者是相同的物质组成的
If the two bodies formed from the same materials,
那么它们的基本成分应该是一致的
their basic composition should be the same.
但是两者却不相同
But they are not.
相互之间的矛盾
This and other inconsistencies
很快就引导天文学家寻求新的思路
soon led fellow astronomers to quest for new ideas
去解释月球的存在
to explain the existence of the Moon.
在19世纪最后的三分之一时期内
In the last third of the 19's century
关于月球起源的先进理论开始出现
advanced theories about the origin of the Moon started to emerge.
1873年法国科学家爱德华·洛希
In 1873 French scientist, Edouard Roche
提出月球只是在地球旁边形成的
proposed that the Moon simply formed alongside the Earth
本质上是由相同的粒子和气体的星云构成的
out of essentially the same nebular cloud of particles and gasses.
但是这个主张有基本的弱点
But this idea had a fundamental weakness.
月球的铁含量比地球低得多
The Moon has a much lower iron content that the Earth.
密度小许多
It's much less dense.
让我们想起月球和她的成分的要紧的事情是
The big thing that we remember about the Moon and its composition is
她没有地球一样的铁核
that it doesn't have any iron core like the Earth does.
所以你看 地球有个非常大的核心
So you look at the Earth, and there is a very large central area
地球重的内部是铁 镍-铁
something like hefty inside of the Earth is iron, nickel-iron
金属流向地球的核心 在那
and that's metal of drain down to the center of the Earth in there.
地球开始形成时是热的
Earth was hot when it formed at the beginning.
月球更多地只是象普通的石块
The Moon is more like just plain rock.
科学家最初推断月球的质量
Scientists initially deduce the mass of the Moon
是通过观察和数学计算
through observation and mathematical calculations.
如果月球是由与地球相同的物质形成的
If the Moon had formed from the same stuff that made the Earth,
那铁的含量应该是相似的
the iron content should be similar.
这是爱德华·洛希无法解释的理论上的漏洞
It was a hole in the theory Edouard Roche couldn't explain.
但是另一个想法随着
But another idea soon followed down the hills
共同成长的假设而来
of the co-accretion hypothesis.
1878年乔治·达尔文宣布了他的月球起源的裂变理论
In 1878 George Darwin announced his fission theory of lunar origin.
这个理论受到了部分人的关注 因为达尔文有个著名的老爸
This idea received some attention in part because Darwin had a celebrated father,
查尔斯·罗伯特·达尔文--的作者
Charles Darwin, author of "Origin of Species".
乔治·达尔文及时摆脱了老爸的影子
In time though, George Darwin stepped out of this father shadow
成为了英国著名的潮汐学领军专家
and became known as England's leading expert on tides.
通过广泛分析潮汐-月球的关系
And through extensive analysis of the tide-moon relationship
乔治·达尔文认识到
George Darwin came to the realization
月球正逐渐地越来越远离地球
that the moon is gradually moving further and further away from the Earth.
这在95年后被证实了
It wasn't proved until 95 years later.
在宇航员登陆月球时
When astronauts landed on the moon,
在月球上安放了一面小镜子
they put little mirrors on the moon.
可以将一束激光射向月球
And you can shine a laser at the Moon
镜子将激光反射回来
and the laser rebounds at the mirror come back
实际上这能够精确地测量地球和月球之间的距离
and you can actually measure the exact distance between the Earth and the Moon.
地月之间的距离正以每年3.8厘米的速度分开
And the rate at which this distance is increasing is 3.8 cm/year.
3.8厘米是1.5英寸
3.8 cm is about an inch and a half.
如果做一个动画来表示的话
If you made a movie extreme timate,
就会看到月球逐渐地远离地球
you will see the Moon moving away from Earth gradually.
这就是我们现在所看到的
That's what we see nowadays.
达尔文开始考虑时间往后推将会发生什么
Darwin began to consider what would happen if we reverse the process,
把动画往后倒转
if you run the movie backwards.
当我们把时间倒转 月球逐步靠近
As we move backwards in time, and the Moon moves closer,
月球的运转和地球的运转
both the Moon's orbit and the rotation of the Earth
越来越快
get faster and faster.
所以当月球最终与地球融合时会发生什么
And so what will happen if then eventually the Moon must
必须要考虑到地球
coalesce with the Earth, and must, must take the Earth.
达尔文对此合乎逻辑的结论是
The logical conclusion for Darwin
快速旋转的地球融化的一部分
was that a portion of the molten rapidly spinning Earth
必定是与主体分离出来
must have separated from the main mass
产生了我们的月亮
and spawn off to become our Moon.
他立即进行数学计算
He immediately began work on mathematical calculations
逆转月球的轨道
to reverse the trajectory of the Moon
完全回到地球为止
all the way back to the Earth.
令人沮丧的是他几乎得到了回到地球的那个点
Frustratingly, he reaches a point where he gets almost to Earth
然而接着却无法更进一步进行下去
and then he couldn't work it out any further.
数学无法更进一步进行下去
The mathematic doesn't let you go any further.
得到的结果是月球
What you get to as a point where the Moon is
围绕着地球急速旋转
whipping around the Earth at a rate of
速度达到每天5圈或6圈
five revolutions a day or six revolutions a day.
所以 她只是…围绕地球急速移动
So, it's just… zooming around the Earth.
是啊 她..在大约
Ok? And it's… it's about
距离地球5000英里的地方
5,000 miles away from the Earth.
数学仍然无法承认达尔文
Still the mathematics did not allowed Darwin
把两个宇宙天体结合在一起
to bring the two cosmic bodies into contact.
分裂理论争论了数十年
The fission theory was debated for decades,
但是科学家最后认定
but scientists eventually concluded
地球与月球之间的相对运动
that the relative movements of the Earth and Moon
不是由此造成的
could not have resulted from it.
地球旋转得太快
The Earth would have be spinning too fast
以至于无法计算出现在的旋转速度
to account for its present rotation rate.
继续寻求月球诞生的解释
The quest for an explanation of lunar creation continued
不久一个新的理论由一位美国人提出了
and a new theory would soon originate with an American.
1909年 托马斯·杰佛逊·杰克逊·希--
In 1909 Thomas Jefferson Jackson See
美国海军上校
was a U.S. naval captain
驻扎在旧金山附近的麦尔岛
based at Mare Island near San Francisco.
他的官方工作是建立美国西海岸的标准时间
His official job was to keep the standard time for the U.S. west coast.
同时杰克逊·希也是位天才的科学家
But See was also a gifted scientist.
作为年轻人 他被培养成为天文学家
As a young man he had trained as an astronomer.
他是美国首位天文学博士
He was one of the first Americans to actually get a doctorate in astronomy.
他去过德国并得到天文学哲学博士
He went to Germany and got a Ph.D. in astronomy
那个 你知道吗 那时几乎闻所未闻
which was, you know, almost unheard of back then.
在19世纪 美国的科学还是死水一潭
The U.S. was still scientifically total backwater in the 1800s.
杰克逊·希的驻扎地麦尔岛有座天文台
See's duty station, Mare Island, had an observatory.
上校的工作有着充裕的时间去探讨理论
And the captain's job allowed him plenty of time to theorize.
他用尽了时间去探讨共同成长和分裂假设
He had spent time analyzing both the co-accretion and the fission hypothesis
这两个月球诞生的理论
regarding the origin of the Moon,
他不相信这些理论
and he wasn't convinced.
托马斯·希逐步地发展了截然不同的概念
Gradually Thomas See developed a completely different idea.
这个概念被称为"捕获理论"
It came to be called "the capture theory".
托马斯·希的理论在本质上表明月球实际形成
Essentially See theorized that the Moon had actually formed
在太阳系里与地球不同的地方
in a different part of the solar system from the Earth
它围绕着太阳运转 就象颗其它的行星
that it orbited the Sun just like the other planets.
但是它有些地方太靠近地球
But that at some point it had moved too close to Earth
并被地球的引力所捕获
and was captured by Earth's gravity.
他提出在外太空存在他称之为阻尼介质的东西
His idea was that there is something that he called the resisting medium
其实我们现在知道那并不存在
in outer space, which we know is not there now.
托马斯·希从来没有充分解释假设的阻尼介质
See never adequately explained what this resisting medium was supposed to be
是不是细小的物质粒子
possibly tiny particles of matter.
不管怎样他肯定那已经不复存在
Regardless he was sure that no longer existed.
他的概念是地球捕获了月球
His idea is that for the Earth to capture the Moon
月球是来自远方
the Moon would have to come in from far away
接着他碰到了所谓的阻尼介质慢慢下降 接着
and then it would hit this resisting medium and slow down and then
逐渐被捕获进入轨道
gradually get captured into an orbit,
可能不是一次 可能有一小段时间
maybe not at once, it may take a little while
逐渐被捕获进入地球的势力范围
to get gradually be captured into Earth orbit.
所以这就象悬崖弹跳者跳跃大桥 下去 上来
So it'd be like a bungee jumper jumping off a bridge, they go down, come back up
近距离的下去上来
not quite as far go down, come back up.
最后终于下降到底部
Then eventually they settle down at the bottom.
托马斯·希的捕获理论的确解释了
Thomas See's capture theory would certainly explain the difference
地球与月球两者铁核的不同
in iron content between the Earth and the Moon.
如果月球是在其它地方形成的 那她的成分就会有很大的不同
If the Moon formed elsewhere its composition could be very different.
另一方面所谓的地球引力捕获和保留
On the other hand the notion that Earth gravity could capture and retain
如此大的物体是不可能的
such a large object was unlikely,
这是因为显然没有阻尼介质
since there is no obvious resisting medium
把月球这么大的物体的速度降下来
to slows down an object as big as the Moon.
所有三个理论都有着重大的弱点
All three theories have significant weaknesses.
月球的起源保持着神秘
The origin of the Moon remained a mystery.
1969年7月20日 美国宇航员首次踏足月球表面
On July 20th 1969 US astronauts set foot on the lunar surface for the first time.
这是人的一小步
That's one small step for man,
却是人类的一大步
one giant leap for mankind.
他们的登月舱登陆在坚硬的火山岩平原
They had landed their lunar module on hardened lava plain
那里叫做宁静海
known as the Sea of Tranquility.
宇航员巴兹·奥尔德林描述了看到的广阔荒凉的景象
And mission pilot Buzz Aldrin described the view as magnificent desolation.
-美极了…-有什么东西吗？
- Beautiful view… - Isn't that something?
下面的景色好宏伟
Magnificent sight down here.
宇航员带回了48磅月球的岩石和土壤
The astronauts brought back 48 pounds of moon rocks and dusty soil,
或风化层
or regolith.
大声清晰地读出你的位置 我们的位置在133 0-69 15
Reading you loud and clear. Our position 133:0-69:15.
休斯敦约翰逊航天中心的地质学家急切地等候着他们的归来
Geologist at Johnson Space Center in Houston eagerly awaited their arrival.
样本第一次被带回的刺激就象触电一样
The excitement when samples first came back was just electrical.
我的意思是 这真是难以置信
I mean, it was just incredible.
没有人真的完全知道自己所期待的
Nobody really knew quite what to expect.
我们立即意识到这块玄武岩
And we realized right away that we had basaltic rocks
就象夏威夷可能会看到的
like one might see in Hawaii.
事实上非常象会在夏威夷看到的石头
In fact very similar to rocks one would see in Hawaii.
美国航天局的地质学家私下希望看到的不仅仅是玄武岩
The NASA geologist were intrigued to find not only basalts
而是另外一种石头
but rocks of another sort.
石头叫角砾岩
Rocks called breccias.
角砾岩形成于小行星撞击
Breccias form during asteroid impacts.
所以你能想象如果一个巨大的物体撞击月球
So if you can imagine a large impact body hitting the Moon it's gonna be
将会非常混乱 将会撞出碎片 碎片将会飞起
very chaotic, it's gonna throw up debris. Debris gonna come flying out this what
形成弹坑 结束后 在月球上看到许多弹坑
ends up to be a crater after it's over and you can see the many craters on the Moon.
碎片乱七八糟地堆积在弹坑的四周
This debris gets all jumbled up and lands on the ground around the crater
接着碎片会由弹坑产生的热融合在一起
and then it gets compacted with the heat generated by the crater
转化成岩石 看起来非常混乱 你瞧
and gets turned into rocks that look very chaotic, you see.
石头里各种碎片有不同的大小
All sorts of pieces in the rock in different sizes
不同的形状 那个区域石头里的所有碎片
different shapes, all pieces of the rock that are in the area that
都是碰撞压实的
impacting body impacted.
在地球上就没有看到过这样的
We have just not seen anything like this on Earth.
月球吃透不久就开始讲述了迷人的故事
The Moon rocks soon began to tell a fascinating tale.
首先石头和土壤的样本包含的粒子
First the rocks and soil samples contain particles
标志了在形成之前月球必定覆盖了厚厚的
indicating that the Moon must have been covered by a deep ocean of lava
广阔的火山熔岩
after it formed.
这个从发现得到的补充概念
This notion was reinforced
是石头缺少值得注意的
by the discovery that the rocks were lacking significantly
被科学家称之为"挥发性成分"的东西
in what scientists call "volatile elements".
挥发性成分是那些容易挥发的元素
Volatile elements are those that can evaporate easily
是在加热石头时会消失的
and they're for be lost when you heat up a rock.
挥发性成分一些例子包括水或钾等等
And some examples of volatile elements include water or potassium for example.
如果将地球岩石与月球岩石比较
And if you compare the bulk Earth rocks to lunar rocks
会发现月球岩石非常的干
you find that lunar rocks are extremely parched.
就象被加热过的
It's like just they've been heated and they've
就象失去了挥发性成分
lost a lot of their volatile elements.
但是顺着这个对比
But along with this start contrasts,
月球样本也显示出在月球表面与
the lunar samples also revealed at least one astonishing similarity
地球上的岩石土壤之间至少有一个令人吃惊的相似之处
between the lunar surface and rocks and soil from Earth.
个别元素的同位素象氧有些特别
The isotopes of individual elements, like oxygen in particular.
氧有不同的形态
There are different forms of oxygen.
月球与地球相比 有这不同形态的相同比率
The Moon had exactly the same ratios of different forms that the Earth did.
但是我们掌握的来自太阳系其它地方的所有石块
But all the other rocks we knew from elsewhere in the solar system
那些从太空落下的陨石 都具有不同的氧同位素的比率
which are meteorites that fall out of space, all have different oxygen isotope ratios.
那些东西表明月球的物质与地球的物质非常非常地相似
Which tells you that the Moon material and the Earth material are very very similar.
最后月球样本提供了关于月球地质构造的
In the end the lunar samples had supplied a will for hard evidence,
一个有力的证据
regarding the geological make up of the moon.
然而天文学家试图了解月球的起源
But astronomers trying to understand the Moon's origin
仍然感到困惑..
were still left with the puzzle.
对于亚利桑那州图森的行星科学学会的威廉·哈特曼
For William Hartmann, of the Planetary Science Institute in Tucson, Arizona,
月球石块透露的一点信息支持了一些想法
the information gleam from the Moon rocks supported some ideas
他几乎研究了十年
he's been working on for nearly a decade.
现在一位著名的天文学家兼太空画家
Now a distinguished astronomer and painter of space images,
60年代早期哈特曼是亚利桑那大学的研究生
in the early 60s Hartmann was a graduate student at the University of Arizona,
参与了一个项目 为月球冲击坑绘制地图
taking part in a project to map impact craters on the Moon.
从巨大的盆地 或许多看得见的最小的坑着手
From the enormous basins, or seas to the smallest visible dimples.
这一切我认识到 在60年代绘制的大盆地的地图
All I realized during this mapping in the 60s
实际上是撞击的特征
that the big basins are actually impact features.
很大的小行星撞击了月球
Very large asteroids hit the Moon
产生了这些巨大的爆发 某些宽达600英里
and made these huge explosions, some of them are 600 miles across.
到底是多大的物体做到了这一点？大概有100英里宽
How big an object does it take to do that? Something like 100 miles across.
所以有大的物体游荡在太阳系里
So we had large object surrounding around the inner solar system
当地球形成时 撞击着行星
as the Earth was forming and they were crashing into planets.
对于那个100英里宽的小行星撞击行星的概念 哈特曼
For Hartman, the notion that a 100 miles wide asteroid once impacted planets
提出了两个问题
bade a couple of questions.
行星大小的物体曾经碰撞过吗？
Could planet sized objects have ever collided?
能够与月球的形成有关联吗？
And could that have something to do with the formation of the Moon?
1972年哈特曼和伙伴图森天文学家唐·戴维斯
By 1972 Hartmann and fellow Tucson astronomer Don Davis
编写了一个计算机程序帮助解决这些问题
had created a computer program to help them explore these ideas.
程序粗略地模拟了
The program made a rough attempt to simulate
早期太阳系的成长过程
the accretion process in the early solar system.
天文学家们希望看到会有其它行星物体
The astronomers wanted to see if any others planetary bodies
在地球附近形成 并能够撞击她
formed near the Earth and could have crashed into it.
这个概念是…如果那里有一些其它的物体
The idea was… if there was some other body there
并且最终撞击地球
and it finally crashes into the Earth,
将从地球撞出这所有的地壳物质…
it blows off all this crustal material from the Earth…
同样也有撞击者自身
As well as from the impacter itself.
可能月球是在那个外面形成的
Maybe the Moon could form out of that.
确实充分的模拟表明第二个行星
Sure enough the simulation showed that a second planet
会在地球默认的地带形成
could have formed in the Earth's acquiescent zone.
其大小相当于火星的大小
One about the size of Mars.
那不是月球 因为它与地球有着相同的元素
It wasn't the Moon because it had formed from the same elements as the Earth
所以它应该有着与地球一样的铁核和密度
and should therefore have had the same iron-core and heavy density as the Earth.
月球当然不是这样的
The Moon of course does not.
哈特曼足够的证据陈述了新的第四个假设
That was evidence enough for Hartmann to formulate a new fourth hypothesis.
被称为 巨大撞击理论
It came to be called: The Giant Impact theory.
1974年 解释地球的卫星来源的新假设
In 1974 a new hypothesis explaining the origin of Earth's moon
登上了世界科学的舞台
debuted on the world scientific stage.
它的支持者赋予它 巨大撞击理论
Its proponents dubbed it: The Giant Impact theory.
基本的概念是大约在45亿年前
The basic idea is that about 4.5 billion years ago
地球被相当于现在的火星大小的物体撞击
Earth collided with an object roughly the size of the current planet Mars.
这是非常巨大的撞击
It's a very large collision.
她使得地球自转
And it started the Earth's spinning.
我们认为她带来了今天的一天24小时
It's what gave us our current 24 hour day we believe.
这个撞击是如此的沉重
And this collision was so massive
使得抛出的物质进入了围绕地球的轨道
that it launched material into orbit around the Earth.
而且对于那些物质 我们认为随后凝聚成了月球
And it's for that material that we believe the Moon later coalesced.
博尔的西南研究学会的罗宾·坎努普博士等人
Dr. Robin Canup and others of the Southwest Research Institute in Boulder
建立了一个计算机模型来研究
have constructed a computer model to study the details
巨大撞击设想的细节
of the giant impact scenario.
她把地球和这个碰撞的粗野的原行星分别
It divides off the Earth and this colliding rough protoplanet
放入不同的粒子 接着不同粒子通过碰撞进行演变
into many different particles and then the evolution of each particle is tracked through the course of the impact.
模拟通过从上往下鸟瞰描述碰撞
The simulation depicts the impact from a bird's eye view from the top-down.
地球甚至在撞击之前可能部分熔化了
The Earth was probably partly molten even before this impact.
所以最初碰撞在这个方向开始
So initially the impacter came in from this direction,
她撞击地球是个偏心的撞击
it hit the Earth with an off-center collision.
可以看到撞击延伸出来
And you can see the impacter has been stretched out
形成物质的长臂 就在这
into this long arm of material, right here.
科学家认为地球的上层
Scientists believe the upper layers of the Earth
随着撞击完全熔化
became completely molten following the impact.
撞击让地球开始旋转
The collision starts the Earth rotating.
同样能够看到撞击
And you can also see that the collision has
充分扭曲了地球本身的形状
substantially distorted the shape of the Earth itself.
几个小时后 看到撞击物质形成的长臂
After a couple hours we see that this arm of impacter material
由于引力崩塌成两个大块
has collapsed gravitationally into two large clumps.
里面的大块
The inner clump of the impacter material
实际上无可厚非 是撞击者的核
is actually composed overwhelmingly of the impacter's core.
所以当这个里面的大块与地球碰撞时
So then when this inner clump recollides with the Earth,
她发生在这里
and it happens right there,
大多数的铁随着碰撞
the vast majority of the iron that came in with the impacter
实际上由地球收集起来了
is actually accumulated by the Earth.
而外面的大块
While this outer clump
靠近地球运行
comes and it makes a close pass by the Earth,
在地球的引力作用下 撕开变为一条物质的长臂
and is stripped by the Earth's gravity into a long arm of material,
接着破裂成为这个圆盘
which then breaks up to form this disk.
上面提到的物质紧接着沉重的撞击
The material is taught to have coalesced to form the Moon in less than an year,
在不到一年的时间里结合形成了月球
following the massive impact.
现在的地球上已经没有那次碰撞的痕迹
There is no sign of this impact on the Earth today
这是因为当时 地球的大小只有现在大小的90%左右
because at the time, our planet it only developed to about 90% of its current size.
余下的10%是在以后的许多小得多的碰撞中形成的
The remaining 10% would accumulate from later much smaller impacts.
地球本身的引力也重新进行了改造
Also the Earth's own gravity had a reshaping effect.
在发生碰撞以后的日子里
Within the day after the impact the Earth had reassumed
地球再次形成了基本的球状
a basically spherical shape.
碰撞引起的所有凹地被抹平了
And any depression that the impact caused would had been smoothed over.
巨大碰撞理论的发明人比尔·哈特曼
Giant Impact theory originator Bill Hartmann
在1974年的科学讨论会上介绍了他的假设
presented his hypothesis at a scientific conference in 1974.
然而在近十年里 很少得到关注
But it received little attention for nearly a decade.
对月球的兴趣在阿波罗任务的最后急剧地降温
Interest in the Moon dropped off sharply at the end of the Apollo missions.
最后在1984年夏威夷的月球研讨会上
Finally at a lunar conference in Hawaii in 1984
距离最后一次月球发射12年以后
twelve years after the last Moon shot,
世界上最大的四个天文学组织达成一个共识
the world's four most astronomers reached a consensus.
巨大碰撞理论是确定月球来源
The Giant Impact theory was the most acceptable explanation to date
最可接受的解释
for the origin of the Moon.
我想还是有人会说 "好啦 至今还是没有被证明啊 "
I think there's still some people who say: "Ok, it's not really proving yet."
但是这就是我称之为有待证明的理论
But it's what I would call the default theory.
如果你翻阅所有行星科学或地质学的教科书
If you look at any textbook of planetary science or geology
这就是公认的理论
it's just the theory that's accepted.
在已经解释的地方必然会有些小的矛盾
And there are certain small discrepancies which have yet to be explained
但是大部分是认可的
but buy in large it works.
即使有一个关于月球来源的意见一致的理论
Even with an agreed-upon theory of how our moon came to be
科学家还是没有结束用各种手段对我们最近的邻居的研究
scientists have not finished studying our closest cosmic neighbor by any means.
事实上讨论重返月球表面建立永久前哨基地
In fact talk of returning to the lunar surface with a permanent end outpost
最近从白宫到航天局开始了
has recently emanated from the Whitehouse at NASA headquarters.
窗前灿烂的光芒
Gorgeous heat is at the window.
一路顺风
Exec-One's good everything go.
这样的基地能够提供训练宇航员长期在太空生活的地方
Such a base could provide a place to train astronauts to live in space long term.
以及提供更有效的发射点 最终实现火星飞行
As well as provide them more efficient launch point for eventual missions to Mars.
但是这崇高的科学目标是来自远方的地球的精神
But such lofty scientific goals are far from the minds of average residence of Earth.
人们偶尔凝视夜晚天空生动催眠的圆月
Who occasionally peer up at the glowing mesmerizing lunar disk in the night sky.
对于我们讨论熔岩海洋…
For us talk of lava oceans…
风化层形成了微小陨石…
Regolith forming micrometeorites…
以及巨大的碰撞…
And giant impacts…
将永远不会削弱我们对那个神秘邻居的魅力与追求
Will never diminish the fascination and romance of our mysterious neighbor-world:
月球
the Moon.
谢谢观赏
Thanks For Viewing